Welcome to Cool Reader

This is a program to read electronic books in a number of formats: EPUB, FB2, RTF, TXT, HTML, CHM, PDB, MOBI, TCR

Save books to read on SD card and open them using internal File Browser, or download them from online catalogs (OPDS) directly in CoolReader.

Navigation while reading

You can move to next / previous page using several methods:

Touch screen: flick right to left for next page, left to right for previous
Touch screen: tap right side of screen for next page, left side for previous page
Turn pages using Volume keys
Using hardware joystick or navigation keys
Turn pages trackball (if present on device).

To navigate by link, long tap on link. To return back, press Back key or long tap top left corner of screen

Links to sections of manual: Menu | Settings | File browser | Tap zones | Bookmarks | Dictionaries | Read Aloud | Automatic page flipping | Zoom images | Advanced configuration | Useful links

You can navigate to specific page by its number using Menu / Goto / Page Number.

You can navigate to percentage position using Menu / Goto / Position percent.

Use Table of Context to navigate by chapters: Menu / Goto / Table of contents.

Menu

To access menu:

Keys: short press menu key
Touch screen: tap center of screen

Menu items:

Open file using file browser
Go to... submenu:

Page number...
Position percent...
Toggle automatic page flip (speed can be changed using volume keys or by tapping on bottom left or bottom right corners of screen)
Table if contents
Back in navigation history
Forward in navigation history
Open previous book

Bookmarks
Select text
Options
Search text
"More" submenu:

Toggle day / night mode
Toggle document styles
Toggle text autoformat (for TXT files)
Read aloud (text-to-speech)
Open previous book
Toggle automatic page flipping
Exit program
About Cool Reader
About current book
Show user manual

Settings

To access Settings, use one of following methods:

Keys: long press menu key
Touch screen: long tap center of screen
Main menu: select Options item from main menu

Settings window has a few tabs

Text settings
Style/CSS settings
Page layout
Controls
Application

Setting profiles

You can use several setting profiles, with fast switching between them. Assign "Switch profile" action on some tap zone or key

Text settings

Font Face
Font Size
Embolden font - make text bolder
Font antialiasing - smooth edges of font glyphs
Interline space - vertical space between lines of text
Hyphenation dictionary - choose dictionary by languages, algoryphmic mode, or turned off.
Floating punctuation - align visually rigth side of width-aligned text, by placing of some narrow punctuation signs outside of align bound.
Font kerning - inter-character distance correction depending on pair of characters
Image scaling options - allow to control usual and inlined in text images scaling
Gamma correction - can change character glyph weight slightly lighter or bolder, and tune antialiasing better for particular font.
Minimum space width - when trying to fit as much text as possible into single line, this option controls whether it's possible to try narrowing spaces to fit more text, and what is minimal width for space between words (in percents of usual space widths, select 100% to disable this feature).
Font hinting - controls behavior of fitting of vector glyph into raster grid. For different fonts, different hinting modes give better result.
Fallback font - font which should be used to show characters missing in main font

Stylesheet settings

Enable document styles - controls whether to use styles defined inside document
Enable document embedded fonts - controls whether to use fonts embedded inside document
Enable text autoformat - controls whether to autoformat (reflow) text or leave as is (and show with monospace font as preformatted text)
Items to change default style sheet for different items in document (normal paragraph, title, subtitle, preformatted text, hyperlink, quotation, etc). You can specify a lot of properties of corresponding elements like font face, style, color, interline space, margins, etc. Actually, these options generate default CSS (cascading style sheet) for documents. Google for CSS manual to learn more about these settings.

Page layout settings

Fullscreen mode - hide status bar. This option may not work on Android 3.0 and 4.0
View Mode - book pages or scroll. I would recommend using Book view.
Page orientation - you can choose portrait, landscape or sensor.
Number of pages (columns) in landscape mode.
Day/Night profile switch (switches between two stored set of properties, like colors, etc.). Night mode uses light text on dark background.
Text color - allows to select solid background color.
Background color - allows to select solid background color.
Background texture - select some image or texture for background.
Title bar options - change appearance on title bar above page.
Footnotes at bottom of screen (currently works for FB2 format only).
Page turning animation mode
Highlight style for bookmarks (disable, solid background, or underline).
Color for text selection highlight
Colors for Comment and Correction bookmarks
Page margins

Controls settings

Keys actions -- allows to select actions for normal, long or double press of some keys.
Tap zone actions -- allows to select actions for normal and long/double tap on each of 3x3 tap zones.
Tap zone secondary action type (long tap or double tap)
Start selection on double tap (or long tap, depending on previous option).
Use volume keys to navigate book
Highlight tap zone on activation
Turn off trackball
Brightness control using left or right screen side flick (disabled, left side, right side).
Gesture page flipping (enable/disable page flipping by finger flick gesture).
Action for single word selection (selection toolbar, copy to clipboard, find in dictionary, add bookmark, find text).
Action for multiple word selection (selection toolbar, copy to clipboard, find in dictionary, add bookmark, find text). Often it's feasible to assign Dictionary for single word selection, and Add Bookmark for multiselection.
Keep selection after dictionary invocation (helps not to forget last reading position).

Application settings

Interface languages - you may use the same language as set in system, or choose different one.
Interface theme (color theme for program interface).
Backlight interval - you can use system setting, or specify your own interval.
Screen backlight brightness - you can select it here, or, may use flick on screen side (if enabled in Settings).
Turn off key backlight - useful for reading in dark.
Show icons for Settings items
Dictionary - select dictionary to use when word is selected, and Find in Dictionary action is chosen.
Covers in file browser.
Scan book properties when entering folder.
Hide directories w/o books.

Tap zones

Screen is divided into grid 3x3 cells called tap zones.

You can specify two actions for each tap zone, for short tap (primary action) and long double tap (secondary action).

Type of secondary action can be selected as long tap or double tap in settings.

Currently selected actions (primary / secondary):

|
|

|
|

|
|

Bookmarks

Coolreader supports 3 types of bookmarks:

Position bookmark: when created, anchor is associated with top line of current page
Comment bookmark: you can add comments for selected text range
Correction bookmark: you can specify corrected text for selected text range (useful for proofreading)

Comment and Correction bookmarks are highlighted

Comment and Correction bookmarks can be highlighted if corresponding option is enabled in settings

To add position bookmark, open Bookmarks window using Menu / Bookmarks, then press Plus sign in window header. Current page will be bookmarked, and next time Bookmarks window is opened, you will see it in list of bookmarks. Press on bookmark item in list to move on bookmarked page

To add comment or position bookmark, you have to select text range.

Double click on word to start selection, then move your finger to select text range.

Long click on word to start selection, then move your finger to select text range.

Alternatively, you can use Menu / Selection to enter selection mode. Then select range of text with finger.

Use Menu / Selection to enter selection mode. Then select range of text with finger.

When selection is completed, Selection Toolbar appears. Press Bookmark button to add bookmark for selection.

When selection is completed, and the only one word is selected, Selection Toolbar appears. Press Bookmark button to add bookmark for selection.

According to current settings, for multiple word selection, no Selection Toolbar will appear. Instead, action assigned in "Multiselection action" setting will be invoked instantly. You can change this behavior in Settings.

When selection is completed, Add Bookmark window will appear instantly. (Alternatively, you can choose another behavior in Settings / Selection Action)

When selection is completed, and the only one word is selected, Add Bookmark window will appear instantly.

According to current settings, for multiple word selection, different behavior is assigned. no Selection Toolbar will appear. You can change this behavior in Settings / Multiselection action.

Add Bookmark window allows you to select type of bookmark, and specify comment (for Comment Bookmark) or corrected text (for Correction Bookmark). Press Plus sign at window title to add bookmark, Back button to cancel.

Comment and Correction bookmarks are highlighted in text.

Comment and Correction bookmarks may be highlighted in text if corresponding option is checked in Settings

To open list of bookmarks, use Menu / Bookmarks. List of bookmarks for current book appears.

Short tap on list item instantly moves reading position to selected bookmark.

Long tap on list item opens context menu for bookmark:

Goto - move to bookmark position in text
Add - add position bookmark for current page
Edit - change comment or correction text
Remove
Export - save list of bookmarks to text file
Send - send list of bookmarks in text format in email, etc.

Dictionary support

Cool Reader can invoke external dictionaries to translate selected word.

Supported dictionary applications (can be installed from Market):

Fora
Color Dict
Color Dict New / Golden Dict
Aard
Dictan

Select dictionary application you want to use in Settings / Application / Dictionary.

Select word you need to translate, then press Dictionary icon in opened selection toolbar.

For convenient use, you can assign Dictionary action on selection, instead of toolbar: Settings / Controls / Selection Action or Multiselection action.

Read Aloud

Cool Reader supports reading of text using Text To Speech engine.

It uses speech engine and voice set in Android system settings as default.

To start reading, use Menu / More / Read Aloud (for faster access, you can assign Read Aloud action to some tap zone or key).

Control panel appears which will let you control reading position, start/stop reading, change pitch and speed.

Automatic page flipping

You can use automatic page flipping. To start, use Menu / Goto / Autoscroll (you can assign this action on some tap zone or key for convenient use).

Adjust speed using volume keys or by pressing lower left and right bottom corners of screen.

To stop autoscroll, tap any place on screen, except bottom left and right corners.

Zoom pictures

Long press on picture to open it in internal image viewer.

Change zoom using + and - icons or using volume keys. Scroll using finger sliding.

To close viewer, press Back key or tap any place of screen except zoom icons.

File Browser

To select book to read, use embedded file browser.

You can go to file browser from reading mode using Menu / Open Book. (To return back into reading mode, you can use Menu / Current book or tap on book file)

File browser allow accessing filesystem tree, list of recent books, books by author/series/title, online OPDS catalogs to download books. Root folder of file browser contains links to all of these sections.

At any place inside File Browser, you can use Menu / Goto items to navigate to browser root page, recent books list, online catalogs.

You need to place your books to internal storage or SD card to read them using Cool Reader.

Cool Reader stores metadata (author, title, series, filename, etc) for books, last reading positions, and bookmarks using internal database.

To import book into database, you have to either enter book's directory or invoke Menu / Scan directory on some directory.

File Browser Topics: File system | Recent Books | Online Catalogs | Books by authors/series/titles | File Browser Menu | File Browser Settings

Browsing file system

Usual way of opening books is to select it directly in file system tree.

In file browser root, you can see items for internal storage and/or external SD card.

Navigate by directories by tapping on them. Return one level up by pressing of upper item.

Long tap on book offers useful actions in context menu: you can open book, delete it, change sorting order, and navigate to file browser root, online catalogs, or recent books.

Menu key allows some additional operations: go back to currently opened book, find book in database, scan file system for book properties, change settings like sorting order or browsing mode (normal or simple), exit application.

There are two modes: normal view (with book metadata like author, title, series, coverpages, etc.) and simple file view (which shows file names only).

Book covers are shown in normal mode only. You can toggle coverpage display in reader mode Settings / Application dialog.

Only for EPUB and MOBY books covers are shown instantly once you enter directory. For FB2 books, cover image will be shown only after opening of book.

Menu / Search allows to find book in database by its metadata (filename, title, author, series name). As well, book catalogs by authors, series, titles are accessible from file browser tree.

Recent books list

Cool Reader holds list of recently opened books.

To enter Recent Books section from File Browser root, choose "Recent Books" item, or use Menu / Goto / Recent books from any place.

Tap on book in list to reopen it. Last reading position will be restored.

By long tapping on recent book item, context menu offers some useful actions: go to book folder in filesystem, remove book from list of recent books, remove book completely, opening of book.

OPDS Catalogs

Cool Reader allows downloading of books from OPDS online catalogs.

To enter Online Catalogs section from File Browser root, choose "Online Catalogs" item, or use Menu / Goto / Online catalogs from any place.

You will see list of available catalogs.

You add, remove, and edit catalog items, by long tap on some item.

Choose one of catalogs, then go through its hierarchy to find some book you need. By pressing on book item, you will start download of this book. Once book is downloaded, it will be opened for reading.

Downloaded files are being stored in Books directory on SD card or internal memory, in subdirectories by authors.

NOTE: secure connections (SSL) are not supported yet.

Books by Author / Title / Series

Cool Reader provides categorised access to books database sorted by book metadata: author, title, series name. You can see corresponding items in file browser root.

Tap on corresponding category item (e.g. "Books by authors" to divide books by author name).

Inside, you can see either category prefix (e.g. first letter(s) of author's name), full category name (e.g. full author name), or book itself.

Cool reader can create subfolders by one, two, etc. first letters of category name, if list would be too long otherwise. (E.g. while there are only 10 authors, you will see all of them directly in list. But if there are 100 authors in database, they will be grouped by first letter (s))

Only books from scanned folders are added into database.

To import book into database, you have to either enter book's directory or invoke Menu / Scan directory on some directory.

File browser menu

Menu items are:

Currently opened book -- back to reading
Find book -- find book by its properties in database
Scan directory -- scan book properties from current directory and deeper
Goto -- navigate to file browser root, recent books, or online catalogs.
Settings -- change some settings (sort order, book item mode).
More: close program, open user manual

File browser settings

Press menu/settings to reach file browser settings menu. Using Settings, you can change book sorting options, and change browser mode from normal to simple and back. You need to restart program to see new fonts in settings.

In simple mode, only file names are shown for books. In normal mode, book titles, authors, series name, file name, cover are shown, if available.

More settings can be found in Reading Mode / Settings dialog. On Application settings tab, you can find following options:

Show book covers in file browser
Scan book properties on directory enter
Hide directories w/o books

Advanced configuration

Additional fonts

You can add more fonts by placing .ttf files to Fonts directory on SD card.

External styles, CSS

For fine tuning of styles, you can change Cascading Style Sheet definition for format. CSS files for different formats (fb2.css, epub.css, htm.css, rtf.css, txt.css, chm.css) can be placed to /.cr3/ directory of SD card. In this case they override internal style in package. As a base, styles from GIT repository of CoolReader (crengine) SourceForge project can be used.

Additional background images

To use your own images (.jpg, .png) as page background in tile mode, place them to /.cr3/textures/ directory of SD card.

Instead of /.cr3/ directory (with period) you can use directory name w/o period (/cr3/) Instead of external SD card, you can use internal storage or internal SD card (if presens in your device)

Howto reset settings

Settings are stored in *.ini files inside /.cr3/ directory on SD card or internal storage (note that .cr3 directory name is started with point, and might be invisible in browser unless "show hidden files" option is enabled)

To reset settings, just remove all files with extension .ini from this directory.

Cache directory cleaning

Possible reason of application crash on book opening is corrupted cache file for the book. You can try to cleanup cache directory manually. Cache files are placed in /.cr3/cache directory on SD card or internal storage (note that .cr3 directory name is started with point, and might be invisible in browser unless "show hidden files" option is enabled). Remove cache directory to resolve problem.

Useful links

(will be opened in external browser)

Project page on SourceForge

Project's Wiki on SourceForge

Project's Donations page on SourceForge

To support project, you can make donations. Easy way to donate project is to buy donation package on Market ("Cool Reader Gold Donation", "Cool Reader Silver Donation", "Cool Reader Bronze Donation"), or buy donation items directly in CoolReader - on third tab of "About Cool Reader" menu item

Send your bug reports to buggins@fromru.com Don't forget to specify your device model, Android version. In case of crash, system logs may help a lot. You can get system logs using Android System Info app (available on market). If some books is failed to open, but other books are being opened ok, or you see that wrong encoding is used to show your book, you can attach book file to bug report email, to simplify investigation.